Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Other Organizations and Individuals, 1920-1966
  This series features a wide range of materials documenting individuals and organizations associated with the three main strands of left-radical political philosophies, political parties, and culture: Communism, Socialism, and Anarchism, including a biographical portrait (released in the early 1930s) of United States Socialist Party leader Eugene V. Debs, with footage of Debs, his wife and his brother; a 1936 newsreel produced by Confederacion Nacional del Trabajo-Federacion Anarquista de Iberica (National Confederation of Labor-Iberian Anarchist Federation," CNT-FAI) and narrated in English by prominent American anarchist exile, Emma Goldman (one of two known extant recordings of the famous orator's voice) of the funeral of the Spanish Civil War anarchist militia leader, Buenaventura Durruti, with footage of Durruti in life, as well as anarchists and members of the Republican Government attending the funeral; the pleasures of Camp Tamiment, a Socialist summer resort in the Pennsylvania's Pocono Mountains, with young adults engaged in a wide range of vigorous outdoor recreational activities and clowning, as well as appearances by Bertha Mailly, Ben Josephson and Algernon Lee, Socialist Party stalwarts and moving spirits and supporters of the Socialist Party-associated Rand School of Social Science; playful scenes from a picnic held by the Hungarian branch of the (U.S. Communist Party-sponsored) International Workers Order; a 1938 May Day Parade (in color and in black and white) in New York City, featuring contingents, floats, banners, and signs with a multiplicity of slogans on contemporary issues, representing the CPUSA and a broad spectrum of Communist Party-associated or left-leaning labor unions and other organizations.
  Organizational life and activities of the New York City-based labor union, District 65-UAW, including a televised membership meeting of department store employees considering a strike, with union president, David Livingston, leading the discussion; a rally (co-sponsored with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People) held in New York City's garment district to protest the murder of Emmett Till, and a short government-sponsored film about an art show by union members.
  The American and international umbrella labor organizations, the Jewish Labor Committee (JLC), and International Labour Organisation (ILO), including a 1920s film about the ILO with exterior and interiors of its headquarters and officials in Geneva, Switzerland; a small amount of footage from the 1935 International Labor Conference, held in Geneva, with a few seconds of the American delegation to the Conference containing what may be the only existing moving images of Grace Abbott (American social reformer, teacher, and writer and colleague of Jane Addams at Hull House); and the Jewish Labor Committee-produced film, Nos Maisons d'Enfants(1949), shot in France (and narrated in Yiddish) to support the JLC's activities on behalf orphaned or destitute Jewish child survivors of World War II.
  Progressive American politicians (mainly from New York City and state), including election campaign speeches, appearances at various events, and endorsements of New York governor Herbert H. Lehman, New York City mayors Fiorello H. La Guardia, William O' Dwyer, Robert F. Wagner, Jr.; city councilmen Paul O'Dwyer and Abraham Beame; and television interviews with United States senator Wayne L. Morse.
  Daily life of poor and working-class children and adults in New York City during the Great Depression, shot by photographer John Albok in black and white and color, including shoeshine boys, children selling flowers, children diving for pennies in the East River, street dancers, and pushcart vendors, homeless African-American adults living under elevated subway train tracks, hungry people rummaging through garbage, and most unique, the JLC-sponsored 1936 "Counter-Olympics" - the World Labor Athletic Carnival, a two-day event held at the City's Randall's Island to protest the holding of the 1936 Olympics in Nazi Germany.
  - Miners; conflict between workers and troops, workers and police; poverty; scenes from inauguration of Franklin D. Roosevelt. Washington, D.C.; New York, NY; Pennsylvania. Stock footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 5:55., 1930-1939, 1966 (Item T 40-H 23)
  - Longuines Chronoscope. Program from the national public affairs television series; this show focuses on a strike in progress by Transport Workers Union's against New York City's private bus lines and features appearance by Michael Quill. New York, NY. Complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 14:57., 1953 (Item T 40-H 0)
  - A campaign statement from New York City CIO Council president, Michael Quill, in which he replies to accusations against him by the Republican candidate for mayor of New York and endorses Democratic mayoral candidate Robert F. Wagner, Jr. New York, NY. Complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 30:04., 1953 (Item T 41-H 1)
  - New York City CIO Council's endorsement of mayoral candidate Robert F. Wagner, Jr. New York, NY. Part of a complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 23:20., 1953 (Item T 41-H 2)
  - Luncheon honoring William O'Dwyer. New York, NY; Hotel Roosevelt, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 11:15., 1953-1959 (Item T 42-H 3)
  - New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. makes speech to (New York City or New York State) CIO Council during his campaign for U.S. Senate. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 26:25., Oct 1956 (Item T 42-H 4)
  - Campaign speech by Democratic-Liberal party candidate for United States Senate, New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. New York, NY; Hotel Commodore, New York, NY. Complete (paid political) television broadcast; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 14:40., 1956 (Item T 42-H 5)
  - Senator Wayne Morse speaks about his opposition to the Kennedy-Landrum-Griffin bill. Washington, DC. Complete television broadcast; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 27:45., Jan 22, 1960 (Item T 43-H 6)
  - Former New York City mayor William O'Dwyer speaks out in favor of organizing civil service workers. Location unknown. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 1:14., undated (Item T 43-H 7)
  - Rally (sponsored by the labor union District 65 and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People) to protest the murder of Emmett Till. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:55., Oct 11, 1955 (Item T 43-H 8)
  - Art. Art show by members of the labor union, District 65. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:05., Mar 1957 (Item T 43-H 9)
  - Art Art show by members of the labor union, District 65. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:10., Mar 1957 (Item T 43-H 10)
  - Strike Report To Stern’s Employees. A meeting of members of labor union District 65, RWDSU to decide whether to strike against Stern’s Department store. New York, NY; District 65 headquarters, 13 Astor Place, New York, NY. Television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 28:45., 1960 (Item T 44-H 11)
  - EUGENE V. DEBS--LABOR'S MARTYR. Biographical sketch of the Socialist Party leader, consisting mostly of stills and titles; released in 1934. Terre Haute, IN. Partial print; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 8:00. (Item T 44-H 12)
  - INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION Three films concerning the International Labor Organization (ILO) Geneva, Switzerland; Lake Geneva, Switzerland. Complete films; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 20:10., 1915-1934, 1932, 1935 (Item T 44-H 13)
  - TALES FROM TAMIMENT Summer activities at Camp Tamiment, a popular resort (in the Pocono mountains) founded by New York City's pioneer workers’ school, the Socialist Party-associated Rand School of Social Science. Bushkill, Pennsylvania. Completed film; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 21:35., 1930-1935 (Item T 45-H 14)
    This material is temporarily unavailable while a new Access DVD is being created.
  - MASS TRIBUTE TO BUENAVENTURA DURRUTI. Memorial to a prominent anarchist militia leader of the Spanish Civil War; narrated by Emma Goldman. Spain; Barcelona, Spain. Complete film; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 11:00., 1936 (Item T 45-H 15)
  - JOHN ALBOK'S DOCUMENTARY FOOTAGE OF New York. Multiple New York City locations, much of it shot during the depths of the Depression of the 1930s. New York, NY; Randall's Island, New York, NY; Central Park, New York, NY; Park Avenue and East 116th Streets, New York, NY; Harlem, New York, NY; East River, New York, NY. Footage; Color and B/W; Silent. Running Time: 30:14., 1929-1955 (Item T 45-H 16, Box 2 (Access DVDs))
  - NOS MAISONS D’ENFANTS. Fundraising film produced by the Jewish Labor Committee to support “children’s homes” established by it in France for war orphans and refugee children. France; Le Mans, France; Paris, France. Complete film; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 9:10., 1948-1949 (Item T 46-H 1)
- Series III: Addendum, 1930-1967
  - Color Tape 1, cuid1032 (Box 34, Item 1)
    BetacamSP, Estimated Duration: 01:00:22, Color
    This tape contains CT 1-H 1, CT 1-H 2, CT 1-H 3, CT 1-H 4
    - May Day rally and demonstration. Includes shots of a young Pete Seeger performing. New York, NY. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 2:55., May 2, 1948; cuid916 (Item CT 1-H 1)
      A digitized copy of this film is available on color tape 1.
    - International Workers Order (IWO) picnic; May Day parade, Union Square, New York City. New York, NY. Union Square, New York, NY. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 9:50., 1930-1939, May 1, 1937; cuid917 (Item CT 1-H 2)
    - New York City May Day parade; New York City Labor Day parade. New York, NY. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 7:38., 1946-1947, Sep 4, 1961; cuid918 (Item CT 1-H 3)
    - THE BEST IS YET TO COME. Documentary produced by the Transport Workers Union that reviews history of the union, its status ca. 1967, and its future. New York, NY; New York Public Library, New York, NY. Complete film; Color and B/W; Sound. Running Time: 29:36., 1962-1972; cuid919 (Item CT 1-H 4)
  - Buses, bus drivers, bus passengers; traffic; subway trains, subway train equipment; views of New York City from elevated subway train. New York, NY. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 22:00, 1967; cuid920 (Item CT 2-H 5)
  - Airport baggage and baggage handlers; airplane maintenance mechanics; jet and propeller airplanes and helicopters. Newark, NJ; Newark Airport, Newark, NJ. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 26:30., 1967; cuid921 (Item CT 2-H 6)
  - Elevated subway trains and New York City landscapes shot from elevated subway trains; subway train repair shop; airport baggage handlers. New York, NY; Far Rockaway, Queens, NY; Gerritsen Beach, Brooklyn, NY; Coney Island, Brooklyn, NY; Brighton Beach, Brooklyn, NY. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 26:16., 1967; cuid922 (Item CT 3-H 7)
  - Railroad train maintenance workers; gas utility workers; Transport Workers Union's Railroad Division president talking with railroad workers. Brooklyn, NY. Footage; Color; Silent. Running Time: 12:30., 1967; cuid923 (Item CT 4-H 10)
  - Transport Workers Union election; rally with speakers; transport workers' demonstration at New York City's City Hall protesting the demolition of elevated subway lines. New York, NY; City Hall, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 29:31., 1930-1949; cuid924 (Item CT 5-H 8)
  - La Parola 34th Anniversary, circa 1942; cuid925 (Box 28, Reel CT-6)